[SPEAKER_01]: I am treating my mind like a wild entity that I must conquer.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I get from your talks on the wild mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rather than getting caught up in its specific emotions, but fighting my mind as if it's a separate enemy,
[SPEAKER_01]: Fighting my mind as a separate enemy creates a painful split inside me.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it feels like.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I maintain the practice of the controller over the mind, or the trainer training the mind, without burning out from this constant internal battle?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the sense of split that might
[SPEAKER_00]: It might feel like... it might feel like that sometimes.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sense of split is not created by you trying to fight the wild animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's created by the fact that the animal is wild.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yes, sure, if you never attempt to train the dog, you'll never realize how wild it was.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you always give it what it wants, you'll think, oh, it's fine, look, we are on the same page.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when you don't give it what it wants, then you realize what a different page that animal is on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yes, the natural kind of immediate response is like, oh, it's because I tried to impose this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, it's because the animal is untrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just your imposing of training or restraint revealed the extent of the wilderness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is no other way around it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you might, if it's too much, yeah, maybe you have to take it more gradually, slower, but, again, you're not going to tame the animal by allowing it
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like it's going to feel burning, the training of something that's wild.
[SPEAKER_01]: Until it calms down, then it won't burn anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you won't have to train it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like, that's... if the measure is, whatever I do that feels like suffering, I mustn't do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well... No, that's a problem then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you would quickly kind of give up the training, basically, if that's your criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: That that mind must... it's like, I'd rather just be one with the mind, just flow with it, do whatever, it feels great.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, until you won't be able to, and then you'll be the one to pay the price, because there's nobody else there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so it seems like quite harsh, like I've got to impose my views, dhamma views, let's say, onto the mind, and just
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, which is like a bit harsh, it's a bit cruel.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to be cruel sometimes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, again, define cruelty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, is it cruel to pull a choking piece of food from the infant's throat?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're probably gonna rip the skin and make some damage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that cruel?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you say by any measure of reason that that is cruel?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, because the bigger picture is you're saving its life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, this is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you lose the sight of the bigger picture, then any infliction of direct or indirect pain is cruel in and of itself, and then you're never going to free yourself, because you need a bigger picture.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need, because it's going to be painful to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, saying no to desire is painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you start doing that,
[SPEAKER_00]: Before things do it for you, by which it's too late to train the mind on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I said in previous talks, it needs to be coming from you, not from the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, any person that was ever in prison or put in solitary confinement would have become an arahant automatically, because things were taken away from them and then...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, but no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to be conveying that message to the mind, not to the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have this, you can't have that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: I decide that, because I recognize what needs to be tamed and trained, and where those underlying tendencies are.